<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>beatltetech.com</title>
 <link href="http://beatletech.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://beatletech.com/"/>
 <updated>2020-08-14T15:36:27+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://beatletech.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Coen Stevens</name>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Chief Architect at Rekall.ai</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2019/09/02/chief-architect-at-rekall-ai"/>
   <updated>2019-09-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2019/09/02/chief-architect-at-rekall-ai</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the past year I have been working as Tech Lead at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airfranceklm.com/en/group&quot;&gt;Air France - KLM&lt;/a&gt;, in the ODS (Operations Decision Support) department. My team was responsible for the on-premise Amsterdam Data Lake, developing ETL pipelines with Spark streaming jobs in Scala, including data modeling of the source system (events) and coordinating with the Data Science team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The on-premise Hadoop cluster was based on Hortonworks HDP, including Spark, HBase, Kafka and Hive. There was a lot of work involved in configuring and managing the on-premise cluster, and we would spend more time than we would like on infrastructure related issues. Based on my previous cloud experiences I started advocating for a push to Azure Cloud (as KLM already had Azure Active Directory and Office 365) for the Data Lake, and started working on the required Architecture design and proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I really liked learning the enormous organization (with two distinct cultures) in order to navigate my way to get in contact with the right people to make Cloud happen, all the way up to CTO and VP levels. I came across another opportunity outside of KLM to work in an environment that was more startup like, more agile, and changing faster with more direct personal impact on the course of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new opportunity, freelancing as Chief Architect at &lt;a href=&quot;https://rekall.ai&quot;&gt;Rekall.ai&lt;/a&gt; to work on data driven solutions powered by Blockchain and AI, is actually where I started today and I’m excited that I’m reunited with some of my former colleagues from &lt;a href=&quot;2015/02/09/bottlenose-series-b&quot;&gt;bottlenose.com&lt;/a&gt;! I’m looking forward to work with an elite team of highly experienced Developers, Designers and Biz Devs. It’s time to go full throttle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rekall.ai&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eu-west-1.beatletech.com/images/logo-rekall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rekall.ai&quot; title=&quot;Chief Architect&quot; width=&quot;80px&quot; height=&quot;80px&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:0px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The post-Persgroep era</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2018/08/06/the-post-persgroep-era"/>
   <updated>2018-08-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2018/08/06/the-post-persgroep-era</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week I finished my job as Lead Data Engineer at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://persgroep.nl&quot;&gt;Persgroep&lt;/a&gt; in Amsterdam, where
I worked for the past year. I had a great time crafting ETL pipelines, writing Scala and Python for Spark (AWS
EMR), scheduling tasks (DAGs) with Airflow, and scaling with Redshift (Minus some boring, but important GDPR
work). But most of all I liked the (Kanban) team, which grew during my time from just 3 members to 15, and I
enjoyed coaching and helping out the new recruits, as well as providing technical support and architectural advise to other teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why leave my esteemed colleagues, when everything is fine and dandy? Can Christian van Thillo really do
without me? (Better known by insiders as Christiaan van de Thillo). Well, I have this tendency to shake things
up once in a while, and I felt the need to explore new startup opportunities. So here we are, I cleared my
schedule for the next half a year, and will be diving into Strong-AI, Genomics, Crypto and Healthcare to find
interesting (and doable) business angles. First I like to explore the latest research and follow a couple of
Coursera courses, while simultaneously hack on some neural nets for crypto value predictions. In other words,
playing around until I hit something concrete and tangible. I have a couple of friends that also have
available overtime to join in on the fun. I’m also keeping an ear to the ground for any other opportunities in
these domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what was the first thing I did last week with my free time? I updated my BeatleTech website, the site you
are actually reading right now! One of my TODOs was to run everything over https, now that Chrome by default
shows your website as not secure when it is served over http
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2018/2/8/16991254/chrome-not-secure-marked-http-encryption-ssl&quot;&gt;news&lt;/a&gt;). This was
relatively easy to fix thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://letsencrypt.org/&quot;&gt;Let’s Encrypt&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://certbot.eff.org/&quot;&gt;Certbot&lt;/a&gt;. As long as you know that Letsencrypt will verify your website over IPv6
if you added an AAAA DNS record, so make sure it points to the correct IPv6 address (mine wasn’t :/ so I
dropped the incorrect AAAA record).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly I was inspired by a Hacker News &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=17671490&quot;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; on improving
your portfolio website, to include a section about my home office setup. I have spent many hours perfecting my
work setup, so it was only logical to also write about it. You can find it
&lt;a href=&quot;https://beatletech.com/Setup&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and in the top menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally after cleaning up my HTML, upgrading Jekyll, minimizing assets and moving them to S3
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/beatlevic/beatletech&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;), I’m concluding my stint on BeatleTech improvements with
this blog post. Next up, research and play time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wish me luck.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Othot raises $1.7 Million</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2016/05/02/othot-raises-capital"/>
   <updated>2016-05-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2016/05/02/othot-raises-capital</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Great news for Othot as they just secured $1.7 Million in their first
round of outside financing. For more details and a shoutout for
Dr. Mark Voortman check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://markets.financialcontent.com/mng-ba.mercurynews/news/read?GUID=32015429&quot;&gt;MercuryNews&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>O Data Scientist, Where Art Thou?</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2015/09/10/o-data-scientist-where-art-thou"/>
   <updated>2015-09-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2015/09/10/o-data-scientist-where-art-thou</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This is a repost of my original blog post at
   &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.othot.com/o-data-scientist-where-art-thou/&quot;&gt;OThot&lt;/a&gt;, where I also work as Senior Data Scientist.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By now you have probably heard about the &lt;strong&gt;“Big Data”&lt;/strong&gt; hype in one form [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/insights/2014/04/big-data-big-hype/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;] or another [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/larrymyler/2015/07/29/big-data-is-a-big-problem-thats-getting-bigger/&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;], or read about how other companies are achieving success harnessing their data [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/howardbaldwin/2015/06/08/whos-ready-for-some-big-data-success-stories/&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;]. With all the attention for Big Data and the accompanied field of Data Science to make sense of the data, it would be no surprise if you want your company to benefit as well from one or more Data Scientists generating actionable insights from your ever-growing sea of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are at this stage with your company and start to search for some great Data Scientists you will quickly find out that these people are in short supply. Now why is that? And why is it potentially dangerous if you simply want to bump or educate one of your company’s developers to a Data Scientist role if your search keeps turning up empty?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why Data Scientists are scarce is twofold. First off, the aforementioned Big Data hype with its growing need for Data Scientists (with the amount of data outgrowing the number of data analysts [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.delphianalytics.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/GrowthOfDataVsDataAnalysts.png&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;]), is creating a high demand for Data Scientists. With many Data Science positions opening up, there is also the troublesome side effect of developers starting to market themselves as Data Scientists, while having zero to none of the required expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, and somewhat problematic, is the required skill set for a Data Scientist. Why problematic? Well, this is expressed clearly in the by now classic illustration of the Data Science skill set, the Data Science Venn Diagram [&lt;a href=&quot;http://drewconway.com/zia/2013/3/26/the-data-science-venn-diagram&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eu-west-1.beatletech.com/images/Data_Science_VD.png&quot; alt=&quot;Data Science Venn Diagram&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:140px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three main skills (indicated by the primary colors) are hacking skills, math and stats knowledge, and substantive expertise. What this implies is that you need to be a programmer and statistician, while also having a lot of experience in these fields and in the relevant problem domain and business context. Given that each of these skills on their own already poses a challenge when you want to find a great candidate, then searching for all of them combined in one person can send you on a wild goose chase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier I mentioned the danger of turning developers (with hacking
skills) into Data Scientists, which if you look at the diagram, might
put you in the Danger Zone! Reason being that if you have hackers
without substantive Math and Statistics knowledge you &lt;em&gt;“[..] give people
the ability to create what appears to be a legitimate analysis without
any understanding of how they got there or what they have created”&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;http://drewconway.com/zia/2013/3/26/the-data-science-venn-diagram&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;]. This could give rise to flat-out wrong business decisions based on wrong interpretations of the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not meant to say that you cannot turn a developer into a Data Scientist, but rather that you have be aware that you also have to teach them the required math and statistics background. Or the other way around, you need to make sure that you are teaching your statisticians to gain better development skills. Nowadays there are many resources on the internet for learning Data Science [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dataquest.io/blog/how-to-actually-learn-data-science/&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;].  This will get you started, but it will take a lot of time and practice to gain enough experience for a desired level of proficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe there might be a better alternative to growing your own in-house Data Science team and that is to have OThot be of service. OThot can either take the Data Science challenge off your hands completely or complement your Data Scientists with substantial expertise in all required skills. So don’t hesitate to reach out if you want to know more about what &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.othot.com&quot;&gt;OThot&lt;/a&gt; has to offer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Big Data, Big Hype? &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/insights/2014/04/big-data-big-hype/&quot;&gt;http://www.wired.com/insights/2014/04/big-data-big-hype/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Big Data Is A Big Problem That’s Getting Bigger: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/larrymyler/2015/07/29/big-data-is-a-big-problem-thats-getting-bigger/&quot;&gt;http://www.forbes.com/sites/larrymyler/2015/07/29/big-data-is-a-big-problem-thats-getting-bigger/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Who is ready for some big data success stories: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/howardbaldwin/2015/06/08/whos-ready-for-some-big-data-success-stories/&quot;&gt;http://www.forbes.com/sites/howardbaldwin/2015/06/08/whos-ready-for-some-big-data-success-stories/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] Growth of Data vs Growth of Data Analysts: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.delphianalytics.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/GrowthOfDataVsDataAnalysts.png&quot;&gt;http://www.delphianalytics.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/GrowthOfDataVsDataAnalysts.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] The Data Science Venn Diagram: &lt;a href=&quot;http://drewconway.com/zia/2013/3/26/the-data-science-venn-diagram&quot;&gt;http://drewconway.com/zia/2013/3/26/the-data-science-venn-diagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6] How to actually learn data science: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dataquest.io/blog/how-to-actually-learn-data-science/&quot;&gt;https://www.dataquest.io/blog/how-to-actually-learn-data-science/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>New Job at ThinkTopic</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2015/06/01/new-job-at-thinktopic"/>
   <updated>2015-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2015/06/01/new-job-at-thinktopic</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two months ago a good friend of mine (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/rosejn&quot;&gt;Jeff Rose&lt;/a&gt;), who is a
former &lt;a href=&quot;http://deepmind.com/&quot;&gt;DeepMind&lt;/a&gt; engineer (acquired by Google), presented me with an
opportunity to come work at &lt;a href=&quot;http://thinktopic.com&quot;&gt;ThinkTopic&lt;/a&gt; to build intelligent tools for a big
publisher that involves image search, collaborative filtering, an intelligent catalog, and much more
by applying Deep Learning techniques for learning in Neural Networks. Additionally most development
work would be done in &lt;a href=&quot;http://clojure.org&quot;&gt;Clojure&lt;/a&gt; (a Lisp dialect on the JVM), which for me really
is the icing on the cake, being a longtime Clojure and functional programming fan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after almost 4 years of working as Chief Architect and Data Scientist at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to take on this new challenge to start working for
ThinkTopic, of which today is my first day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time at Bottlenose working with a great group of people. It has been amazing to see
the company grow to where it is right now, and the potential of where it could go. Getting the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://beatletech.com/2015/02/09/bottlenose-series-b/&quot;&gt;KPMG investment&lt;/a&gt; has been a great milestone
and together with all the work over the years the idea of no longer being part of Bottlenose feels a
bit weird. Bottlenose has given me a lot in terms of experience, joy and friendships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having said that, I’m keeping my desk at the Hackers and Founders building in Amsterdam, so I’m not
going cold turkey on my former colleagues (only switching rooms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to go on this new ThinkTopic adventure, which for today means diving back into
Convolutional Neural Networks. May the fun and challenge begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eu-west-1.beatletech.com/images/thinktopic-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;ThinkTopic&quot; width=&quot;646&quot; height=&quot;195&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:60px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Goodbye P-values, Hello Bayesian Statistics!</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2015/05/17/goodbye-pvalues-hello-bayesian-statistics"/>
   <updated>2015-05-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2015/05/17/goodbye-pvalues-hello-bayesian-statistics</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This is a repost of my original blog post at
   &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.othot.com/goodbye-p-values-hello-bayesian-statistics/&quot;&gt;OThot&lt;/a&gt;, where I also work as Senior Data Scientist.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In statistics there is the old and ongoing debate of Frequentism versus Bayesianism, which has been humorously depicted in the following popular XKCD cartoon [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xkcd.com/1132/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/frequentists_vs_bayesians.png&quot; alt=&quot;Frequentism vs Bayesianism&quot; width=&quot;468&quot; heigth=&quot;709&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:150px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this cartoon we see the Frequentist statistician believing that the odds (p-value) of the
neutrino detector lying are below the (arbitrary) significance level of 0.05, saying that it is
unlikely that machine is lying, therefore concluding that the Sun must have exploded. The
Bayesianist on the other hand also takes his prior knowledge about the Sun into account and
determines that given the billions of years track record of the Sun not exploding vastly outweighs
the likelihood of the neutrino detector lying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of explicit priors with Bayesianism versus implicit priors with Frequentism (yes there are
priors, but they are fixed), is one difference most statisticians know about. However there are
actually more subtle differences that carry big consequences that can sometimes lead to
contradictive conclusions between the two approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The popular blogging site &lt;strong&gt;“Pythonic Perambulations”&lt;/strong&gt; has a great series of technical posts that give
a practical introduction to Frequentism and Bayesianism [&lt;a href=&quot;http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/frequentism-and-bayesianism-a-practical-intro/&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;], which are highly recommended. In this
series Jake Vanderplas explains with great clarity the differences, which are summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Frequentists and Bayesians disagree about the definition of probability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Frequentism considers probabilities to be objective and related to frequencies of real or hypothetical events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bayesianism considers probabilities to be subjective and measures degrees of knowledge or belief&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result he explains: &lt;em&gt;“[..] frequentists consider model parameters to be fixed and data to be
random, while Bayesians consider model parameters to be random and data to be fixed.”&lt;/em&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/frequentism-and-bayesianism-3-confidence-credibility/&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This actually has far stretching consequences for the use of Frequentism in Science, where you most
often have one dataset (i.e., fixed data) for which you want to make inferences, and you are not
interested in inferences for hypothetical other datasets. Using Frequentism in science answers the
wrong question, because you want answers for your specific dataset. Therefore the use of p-values
and confidence intervals in this context are useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you might ask, why then is the use of p-values the de facto standard in scientific research, if
it is fundamentally wrong? Good question. The problem is that confidence intervals are easy to
compute and often give similar results to the Bayesian approach. This doesn’t change the fact that
the approach is flat out invalid, and doesn’t support the conclusions made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently the science community started acknowledging this fact and we are now starting to see
journals, e.g., &lt;strong&gt;“Basic and Applied Social Psychology”&lt;/strong&gt; [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01973533.2015.1012991&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;], where research using p-values is being
rejected. This has not gone unnoticed as both Nature, the international weekly journal of Science,
as well as Scientific American, wrote about it in depth and both proposed Bayesian statistics as a
good alternative. [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/news/statistics-p-values-are-just-the-tip-of-the-iceberg-1.17412&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;][&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/scientists-perturbed-by-loss-of-stat-tools-to-sift-research-fudge-from-fact&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scientific American article adds the following about p-values, and confirms the aforementioned
hypothetical other datasets problem with Frequentism:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Unfortunately, p-values are also widely misunderstood, often believed to furnish more
information than they do. Many researchers have labored under the misbelief that the p-value gives
the probability that their study’s results are just pure random chance. But statisticians say the
p-value’s information is much more non-specific, and can interpreted only in the context of
hypothetical alternative scenarios: The p-value summarizes how often results at least as extreme as
those observed would show up if the study were repeated an infinite number of times when in fact
only pure random chance were at work. This means that the p-value is a statement about imaginary
data in hypothetical study replications, not a statement about actual conclusions in any given
study”&lt;/em&gt;
[&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/scientists-perturbed-by-loss-of-stat-tools-to-sift-research-fudge-from-fact&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, but at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.othot.com&quot;&gt;OThot&lt;/a&gt; we are big proponents of the Bayesian approach for statistical inferences. In a previous blog post by Mark Voortman [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.othot.com/what-do-searching-for-a-plane-and-a-doctors-diagnosis-have-in-common&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;], we already started talking and explaining the Bayesian approach and you can safely bet to expect more of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sources&quot;&gt;Sources&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] XKCD: Frequentists vs. Bayesians &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xkcd.com/1132/&quot;&gt;http://www.xkcd.com/1132/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Frequentism and Bayesianism: A Practical Introduction
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/frequentism-and-bayesianism-a-practical-intro/&quot;&gt;http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/frequentism-and-bayesianism-a-practical-intro/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Frequentism and Bayesianism III: Confidence, Credibility, and why Frequentism and Science do not Mix
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/frequentism-and-bayesianism-3-confidence-credibility/&quot;&gt;http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/frequentism-and-bayesianism-3-confidence-credibility/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] Journal of Basic and Applied Social Psychology &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01973533.2015.1012991&quot;&gt;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01973533.2015.1012991&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] Statistics: P values are just the tip of the iceberg &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/news/statistics-p-values-are-just-the-tip-of-the-iceberg-1.17412&quot;&gt;http://www.nature.com/news/statistics-p-values-are-just-the-tip-of-the-iceberg-1.17412&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6] Scientists Perturbed by Loss of Stat Tools to Sift Research Fudge from Fact &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/scientists-perturbed-by-loss-of-stat-tools-to-sift-research-fudge-from-fact&quot;&gt;http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/scientists-perturbed-by-loss-of-stat-tools-to-sift-research-fudge-from-fact&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7] What Do Searching For a Plane and a Doctor’s Diagnosis Have in Common? &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.othot.com/what-do-searching-for-a-plane-and-a-doctors-diagnosis-have-in-common&quot;&gt;http://www.othot.com/what-do-searching-for-a-plane-and-a-doctors-diagnosis-have-in-common&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My recent Coursera journey</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2015/02/11/coursera-courses"/>
   <updated>2015-02-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2015/02/11/coursera-courses</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of months I managed to complete 4 online courses on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://coursera.com&quot;&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt;, which is an education platform that partners with top universities
to offer free &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massive_open_online_course&quot;&gt;MOOCs&lt;/a&gt; (Massive open online
courses). In this post I like to present you my experiences with these courses and my plans for any
future courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for me to start following online courses has to do with what I already pointed out in my
previous blog post “&lt;a href=&quot;http://beatletech.com/2015/02/03/my-system-to-win-big&quot;&gt;My System to Win Big&lt;/a&gt;”. I want to
keep on improving myself and acquire more knowledge in domains of my interest. Part of it is
revisiting knowledge I’m “supposed” to know to gain an even better understanding, and the other part
is exploring new uncharted territories. I also wanted to follow courses where I would have to
practice and hone my programming skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why follow online courses with a rigid schedule and deadlines if you can simply study books or solve some tough problems on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://projecteuler.net/&quot;&gt;Project Euler&lt;/a&gt; at your own pace? Well, for me as it turns out, having a fixed
course schedule releases me of the burden of planning and serves as a nice stick to finish on time,
which made it easier to get into the habit of spending evening hours on education. This way I didn’t
have to spend my will-power every time to get started, and now that I have grown this study habit and
with it the discipline to follow through, I’m in a much better position to also study at my own pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The courses for which I have received statements of accomplishment are in chronological order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/ml&quot;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/algo&quot;&gt;Algorithms: Design and Analysis, Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/bioinformatics&quot;&gt;Bioinformatics Algorithms, Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/learning&quot;&gt;Learning How to Learn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the subsequent sections I will describe each course and my experiences in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;courses&quot;&gt;Courses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;machine-learning&quot;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Stanford University // June-September 2014 // 12 weeks of study // 6 hours per week // &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/ml&quot;&gt;Coursera link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Difficulty:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Easy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half a year ago at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt; I was shifting from primarily a Software
Architect role to more of a Data Scientist role, and therefore spending more time on Machine
Learning problems. So I thought it was valuable to refresh my knowledge in this particular
domain. Besides reading up on some study books I decided to enroll in the Stanford Machine Learning
course, which presented a nice overview with some basic programming exercises. Topics included (as
listed on the Coursera page):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supervised learning (parametric/non-parametric algorithms, support vector machines, kernels,
neural networks).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unsupervised learning (clustering, dimensionality reduction, recommender systems, deep learning).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best practices in Machine Learning (bias/variance theory, innovation process in machine learning and AI).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that I was already very familiar with these topics, combined with an excellent presentation by
instructor &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/instructor/andrewng&quot;&gt;Andrew Ng&lt;/a&gt;, it may not come as a surprise that I found the
course easy to follow and the programming exercises not hard to implement with only the (frequent)
annoyances of coding in Matlab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It felt good to revisit all the topics in the course, which presented me once again with the wide
variety of Machine Learning approaches and techniques. Perhaps in hindsight other specialized
courses on Machine Learning on a more graduate level would have been more worthwhile. However, I
don’t regret my time spent on this course as it never hurts to go back to the basics once in a
while.  Additionally, as this was my first online course, it was a great way to get started with
Coursera and familiarize myself with this new educational format. And after finding out that it
worked really well for me, I instantly signed up for a lot of other (more specialized) courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;algorithms-design-and-analysis-part-1&quot;&gt;Algorithms: Design and Analysis, Part 1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Stanford University // October-December 2014 // 6 weeks of study // 7 hours per week
// &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/algo&quot;&gt;Coursera link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Difficulty:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Medium&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing the Machine Learning exercises in Matlab I wanted my next Coursera course to require
a “real” and more interesting programming language, and at the time I was already reading up on two
other programming languages that I liked to put into practice: &lt;a href=&quot;http://julialang.org/&quot;&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rust-lang.org/&quot;&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was already aware of the “Algorithms: Design and Analysis” class, which two of my friends already
completed and recommended, thereby making it interesting candidate as my next course. Having finished a similar
course (in Java) during my study at Delft University I thought this course would be a walk in the park and a
good playground for testing the waters with Julia and Rust. At the same time I was starting with the
“Bioinformatics Algorithms” class, which also focused on implementing algorithms, but in the domain of biology
(more on Bioinformatics later). Both courses I started with Julia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can honestly say that I really like the Julia language, which was born out of its creators wish to
have a programming language that is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;… open source, with a liberal license. We want the speed of C with the
  dynamism of Ruby. We want a language that’s homoiconic, with true macros like Lisp, but with
  obvious, familiar mathematical notation like Matlab. We want something as usable for general
  programming as Python, as easy for statistics as R, as natural for string processing as Perl, as
  powerful for linear algebra as Matlab, as good at gluing programs together as the shell. Something
  that is dirt simple to learn, yet keeps the most serious hackers happy. We want it interactive and
  we want it compiled.&lt;br /&gt;
  (Blog:  &lt;a href=&quot;http://julialang.org/blog/2012/02/why-we-created-julia/&quot;&gt;Why we created Julia&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first week’s programming assignment, a counting algorithm piggy backing on merge-sort, I also
implemented in Rust after finishing the Julia version. The Rust implementation was a painful
delivery, which was mostly me fighting the compiler and having a hard time finding clues on the web
due to a lot of breaking changes in Rust’s development towards the 1.0 release version. Add to that
the resulting performance being slower than with my Julia implementation, and I quickly decided to
leave Rust alone or at least until the language would be more stable (1.0 alpha was released Jan
2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was getting the hang of Julia, I also started exploring possibilities to introduce the
language at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;, but found the language too immature just yet (at
version 0.3), especially compared with Python and its vast amount of available (scientific)
packages. It would have been interesting to complete the entire course in Julia, but I deemed it
more valuable to switch to Python along the way and perhaps revisit Julia again in a couple of
years from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now turn to the actual course contents after this (quite long)
Julia-Rust-experience-intermezzo. When I mentioned that I believed this course to be an easy ride, I
was actually quite mistaken. The lectures had a lot of technical and mathematical depth, and the
quizzes were often very challenging. You simply cannot fly through this course without a good
understanding of the introduced concepts, which are luckily very well presented by course instructor
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/instructor/~214&quot;&gt;Tim Roughgarden&lt;/a&gt;. All in all I can highly recommend this
course for both expert and aspiring computer scientists for learning (or revisiting) several
fundamental principles of algorithm design, and I’m looking forward in participating in Part 2 of
this course later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;bioinformatics-algorithms-part-1&quot;&gt;Bioinformatics Algorithms, Part 1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;UC San Diego // October 2014 - Feb 2015 // 10 weeks of study // 10 hours per week //
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/bioinformatics&quot;&gt;Coursera link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Difficulty:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Medium/Hard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always had a general interest in biology with genetics in particular, and if you combine this with
my interest in algorithms and Data Science, you can see why I had a course in bioinformatics high on
my wish list. Along came “Bioinformatics Algorithms” on Coursera and I could no longer resist
signing up and was eager to get started. The syllabus consists of chapters of the interactive text
book
&lt;a href=&quot;http://bioinformaticsalgorithms.com/&quot;&gt;“Bioinformatics Algorithms: an Active Learning Approach”&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where in the Genome Does DNA Replication Begin? (Algorithmic Warmup)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How Do We Sequence Antibiotics? (Brute Force Algorithms)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Which DNA Patterns Act As Cellular Clocks? (Randomized Algorithms)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How Do We Assemble Genomes? (Graph Algorithms)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How Do We Compare Biological Sequences? (Dynamic Programming Algorithms)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are There Fragile Regions in the Human Genome? (Combinatorial Algorithms)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way this was the “Algorithms: Design and Analysis” course all over again applied to the
biological domain. The practical application of the algorithms really made this course stand out for
me, and made all algorithms more tangible. The interactive book accompanied by the online lectures
had great production value and introduced concepts and terminology very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programming assignments throughout the book were the real meat of the course, and it is where
you will spend most (90%) of your time. Where most exercises were not too hard, there was still a
big chunk of problems that were very challenging. Sometimes due to the automated solution checker
that would be a bit too strict in the solutions it would accept (and no feedback on why you were
wrong), but mostly it were just hard problems to solve. Once you worked your way through the chapter
and finished all the exercises, the corresponding quiz was easy to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a statement of accomplishment you needed to score 70%, which is definitely doable. I went the
extra mile and focused on scoring above 85% for an accomplishment with distinction, which meant no
hiding from the difficult parts. In the end I was very proud that I achieved my statement of
accomplishment with distinction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to part 2 of the course, which will start this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning-how-to-learn&quot;&gt;Learning How to Learn&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;UC San Diego // January 2015 // 4 weeks of study // 2 hours per week // &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/learning&quot;&gt;Coursera link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Difficulty:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Very easy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are spending your spare time following online courses and you notice there isn’t enough
time in the week to follow all the courses you would like, you have to make choices. And it is not
only the choices that are difficult, you also want the courses that you decide to follow to have a
lasting impact and not be quickly forgotten when you are moving on to another course. This brings us
to the topic of how you can learn to learn more effectively, which is what the course “Learning how
to learn” has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the course is very easy and lacks real depth, it is still beneficial to at least watch the
lectures and the interviews, as there might be some tips and tricks you can pick up that will
improve your learning capabilities and help you overcome procrastination when it hits you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My key takeaway points are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recall: A great way to improve your understanding and ability to form strong memories is to pause
for a moment after you have read some text, look away, and forcing yourself to recall what you
just read. Formulating your thoughts really helps, so talking and explaining to others is another
big plus.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on “process” not “product”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make to-do lists for next day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exercise really helps when you get stuck on some hard problem. Shifting you focus can make your
subconscious and diffuse mode of thinking work for you in the background.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skim through an article or paper to get a sense of of the context to help structuring new knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015 I want at least take the following courses, of which the first two are continuations of
two courses I already completed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/algo2&quot;&gt;Algorithms: Design and Analysis, Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/bioinformatics2&quot;&gt;Bioinformatics Algorithms, Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/pgm&quot;&gt;Probabilistic Graphical Models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally I’m looking forward to follow more courses specialized in the field of bioinformatics
(e.g. genetics, bio-medicine, evolution, neuroscience) and Data Science (mining datasets, pattern
discovery, advanced statistics)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to finish
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/linearprogramming&quot;&gt;Linear and Integer Programming&lt;/a&gt; of which I
already completed 2 out of 7 weeks, but discontinued the course due to time constraints of other
overlapping courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips&quot;&gt;Tips&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to conclude with two tips for when you are going to embark on your own Coursera journey:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do no take too many courses at once. It might seem sometimes that you could easily squeeze in
another course, but they often take more time than you anticipate. Additionally if you end up
stalling in one or more courses, you might get demotivated and stop all-together.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find yourself some friends who are already following online courses or talk them into joining
you. Having a study group of like-minded individuals will really help you stay on course and make
the ride less lonely and a lot more fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck with our own online education!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bottlenose scores $13.4 Million</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2015/02/09/bottlenose-series-b"/>
   <updated>2015-02-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2015/02/09/bottlenose-series-b</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One and a half years after securing our
&lt;a href=&quot;http://beatletech.com/2013/07/30/bottlenose-secures-four-million/&quot;&gt;$3.6 Million&lt;/a&gt;
series A investment round to bring ‘Trendfluence’ to the enterprise, we are now
proud at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt; to have raised (and
continue to raise) our series B round with a staggering amount of $13.4
Million, bringing the total raised funds north of $17 Million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in December we already disclosed that KPMG International took a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/kpmg-capital-takes-equity-stake-in-bottlenose-a-pioneer-in-real-time-trend-intelligence-300005792.html&quot;&gt;“substantial equity share”&lt;/a&gt; in Bottlenose, but did not yet reveal the
size of the investment nor names of other investors that were ready to
follow KPMG Capital’s lead. Today Techcrunch reported on our Series B
round, listing our additional investors and describing our growing
capabilities in enterprise (real-time) stream data analytics. The
series B round is still open and we plan to raise significant venture
debt on top of the $13.4 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Bottlenose we have exciting times ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the full story on &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2015/02/09/bottlenose-series-b/&quot;&gt;Techcrunch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My System to Win Big</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2015/02/03/my-system-to-win-big"/>
   <updated>2015-02-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2015/02/03/my-system-to-win-big</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in January 2014 I read a book by Scott Adams (of Dilbert fame) titled:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17859574-how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big&quot;&gt;“How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big”&lt;/a&gt;.
The book was brought to my attention when I was reading up on some interesting research and ideas on
passion and discipline (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qwOdU02SE0w&quot;&gt;Carl Newport&lt;/a&gt; comes to mind,
explaining why following your passion is bad career advice). Reading Adam’s book definitely struck a
chord with me and even motivated me to change my work flow and long-held believes on what to focus on
in life. Two things stood out for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Passion is bullshit. It is only after you have put in the work and are lucky enough in having
success that passion comes, not before.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goals are for losers. Systems are for winners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before reading the book I have often asked myself questions like: What is my greatest passion and am I working
every day on the things I’m most passionate about? What kind of startup or company would fit my passion? I
often had a hard time trying to find the perfect answer to these questions, which resulted in
inertia to get started and in some cases I was setting myself up for ever higher and greater goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading about the system approach as an alternative to goal setting made a lot of sense to me. The
system approach can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create habits and reserve your will-power for learning new habits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reduce daily decisions to routine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid setting (high) goals, instead have a system that will keep you going&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keeping up your personal energy, which is your primary metric&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simplicity is key&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A system will keep you going, also in moments of failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key points here is the creation of (good) habits and the discipline to carry it out. A
recent blog post titled:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wisdomination.com/screw-motivation-what-you-need-is-discipline/&quot;&gt;“Screw motivation, what you need is discipline”&lt;/a&gt;
argues for the same point. It basically boils down to growing habits and not let yourself be driven by your emotional state.
So stop waiting until you feel good (enough) to start a particular task and get into the habit of allocating
time to just do stuff to get things done. Focus on the process (your system) and not the product
(deliverables and goals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in general you want to be the most productive you can be, for me having a family with the third kid
on his way (due any moment now), you have to get even more organized and disciplined to get things
done. The way in which I manage this is what I want to present to you
next by outlining my system along several dimensions that Scott describes in his book. I have been adhering to this system for a full year and besides some
minor changes and occasional missteps I’m still following through and it has definitely made a
hugely positive impact on my life and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now without further ado, My System to Win Big:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;exercise&quot;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One or more of the following activities I do daily for at least 30 to 60 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Running&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sprinting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push-ups / Sit-ups / Plank / Triceps-dips / 7-minute workout cycles (Honestly this is the one I
want to become more of a routine several days a week.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Walking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cycling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sports&quot;&gt;Sports&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Football (Soccer)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kickboxing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sleep&quot;&gt;Sleep&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say you need a good amount of sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to bed before 00:00 (Yes, this one is hard if you do remote work for US companies from Europe)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sleep 8 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;flexible-schedule&quot;&gt;Flexible schedule&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being flexible here means being in charge of your own schedule. Making a fixed planning and schedule for
things you want to do is highly recommended for young parents, as long as you are the one who chooses
to make time for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan holidays/time-off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan fixed slots for daily exercise and sports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan stuff that makes you want to get out of bed for it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;diet&quot;&gt;Diet&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m a big proponent of the Paleo lifestyle, and try to avoid as much processed foods as possible and
keeping it real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only occasionally bread/rice/potatoes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No Candy/Cookies/Chips&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No Sodas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No Coffee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Occasionally alcohol (celebrations)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meal skipping is good&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fasting once in a while is great (irregular intervals)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Snacks: nuts and fruits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Eating more vegetables by improving seasoning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Starches like Oatmeal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;steadily-improving--skills&quot;&gt;Steadily improving / Skills&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming (Python, Clojure, Julia, Euler, Math)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book reading / knowledge gathering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blogging (on side-projects / programming)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practicing playing the Piano (still a noob here)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.coursera.com&quot;&gt;Coursera courses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;imagine-an-incredible-future&quot;&gt;Imagine an incredible future&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;related: stay optimistic and opportunistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;help-others&quot;&gt;Help others&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be there for my kids and wife&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offer free advice and guidance for start-ups and companies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engage at meetups and help people out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;show-gratitude&quot;&gt;Show gratitude&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value what you already have&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enjoy the moment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;have-a-healthy-dose-of-stoicism&quot;&gt;Have a healthy dose of Stoicism&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid the pursuit of materialistic goals and don’t get attached to stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;Final words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My system helped me become more productive and happier overall, which
may not yet be the fame and fortune that Scott Adams achieved, but it is
still a big win to me, and I’m ready when any big opportunity arises
in the future to take it head on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course my system isn’t perfect. Of course my system is tailored to suit me and can be different for you.
Of course I’m still failing every so often, but at least I have my system to hold on to and to
remind me how I want things to go. Get your self into the habit of working on what matters to you
and with a little bit of luck and serendipity you can win big too!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Project brAIn</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2014/09/03/project-brain"/>
   <updated>2014-09-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2014/09/03/project-brain</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After years of talking and thinking about creating our own Artificial Intelligence (AI), &lt;a href=&quot;http://linkedin.com/in/markvoortman&quot;&gt;Mark Voortman&lt;/a&gt; and I finaly decided a couple of months ago to actually start working on it. So project brAIn was born. With brAIn we have the modest goal to build an AI that will change the world as we know it. Using Deep Learning techniques we are building towards some cool applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have launched a new website and wrote an &lt;a href=&quot;http://br-ai-n.com/2014/09/03/introducing-brain/&quot;&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt; with more details on our goals and progress. So check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://br-ai-n.com&quot;&gt;br-ai-n.com&lt;/a&gt; and stay tuned for future posts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eu-west-1.beatletech.com/images/screenshot-brAIn-v0.0.2.png&quot; alt=&quot;br-ai-n.com&quot; height=&quot;485&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dokzorg.nl live!</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2013/10/12/dokzorg-live"/>
   <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2013/10/12/dokzorg-live</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I ordered two dedicated machines at Hetzner for myself to develop and run some side projects on a Node.js/MongoDb/Elasticsearch stack.
While these are work in progress, I also finished moving BeatleTech.com to my new server (previously hosted by TransIp) and decided to help out my spouse by
building a website for her freelancing GP (Huisarts) practices. The end result is here today, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://dokzorg.nl&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Dokzorg.nl&lt;/a&gt; is live as of now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She basically wanted a simple landing page with just enough info to get potential employers excited and be findable on the web, without explicitly creating
an online presence by blogging and tweeting. We currently like the end result and hope others like it too. See below for a screenshot of the landing page, and follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://dokzorg.nl&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt; to check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eu-west-1.beatletech.com/images/dokzorg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dokzorg.nl&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now after spending some time front-end developing this project,
I’m looking forward to dive back in the other back-end projects I have going for which I can happily ignore HTML and CSS..&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bottlenose secures $3.6 Million</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2013/07/30/bottlenose-secures-four-million"/>
   <updated>2013-07-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2013/07/30/bottlenose-secures-four-million</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bottlenose just secured a $3.6 Million series A round to bring
‘Trendfluence’ to the Enterprise. With Bottlenose enterprise, while
currently in private beta, we already work with several large brands and
agencies (Pepsi, FleishmanHillard, Razorfish, and DigitasLBi) that
leverage Bottlenose Enterprise for tracking live and emerging trends
and events, directing advertising and marketing initiatives, engaging
customer communities and gathering industry intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the actual press release please check out &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;quot;http://www.novaspivack.com/business/bottlenose-series-a-to-bring-trendfluence-to-the-enterprise&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Nova
Spivack’s blog&lt;/a&gt;
(Bottlenose CEO), or the Techcrunch &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;quot;http://techcrunch.com/2013/07/30/social-media-dashboard-bottlenose-raises-3-6m/&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can keep current momentum at &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;quot;http://bottlenose.com&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;, then we have a bright
future ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Amsterdam Node meetup group</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2012/04/16/amsterdam-nodejs-meetup"/>
   <updated>2012-04-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2012/04/16/amsterdam-nodejs-meetup</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We (me and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dominiek.com/&quot;&gt;Dominiek ter Heide&lt;/a&gt;) started a new &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/amsnode/&quot;&gt;meetup group&lt;/a&gt; in Amsterdam
for anyone interested in Node.js. We had our first meetup 2 weeks ago,
where Dominiek gave a great introduction to Node, the guys from
Rockstart startup &lt;a href=&quot;http://beta.wercker.com/&quot;&gt;Wercker&lt;/a&gt;
(Continuous deployment made easy) gave a nice overview of all the Node
modules they use, and I gave a talk on when to use
Node and my lessons learned while using Node in my previously Y
combinator funded startup &lt;a href=&quot;http://newcope.com&quot;&gt;Newcope&lt;/a&gt; and in
my current job as Chief architect at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We plan to have the Node meetup bi-monthly on the last Thursday of the
month, so the next meetup will be May 31th at 7:00PM. We
have some interesting speakers lined up so I hope to see you all at our
next or future meetups. You can follow any announcement on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/amsnode/&quot;&gt;meetup.com&lt;/a&gt; of follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/amsnode&quot;&gt;us&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:800px;text-align:center&quot; id=&quot;__ss_12232685&quot;&gt; &lt;strong style=&quot;display:block;margin:12px 0 4px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/beatlevic/when-to-use-node-lessons-learned&quot; title=&quot;When to use Node? Lessons learned&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;When to use Node? Lessons learned&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/12232685&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;355&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;padding:5px 0 12px&quot;&gt; View more &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;presentations&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/beatlevic&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;beatlevic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Node.js = #winning&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for those of you who love Clojure or like to know more about it,
check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/The-Amsterdam-Clojure-Meetup-Group/&quot;&gt;
Amsterdam Clojure meetup.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bottlenose 2012</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2012/01/04/bottlenose-2012"/>
   <updated>2012-01-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2012/01/04/bottlenose-2012</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The past couple of months I have been busy working for &lt;a href=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;, for which I did some work
before (earlier in 2011). As I wrote about Bottlenose in a previous
post, it is a really cool (American) tech startup partly based in the
Netherlands that is building a new social assistance application that
helps you make sense of all your social activity streams. It helps
navigate the depths of your networks and keep up with your social
streams so you can engage more intelligently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoy working on all the technical challenges that we need to
tackle to create a smart and intelligent client. Challenges involving:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Natural Language Processing (NLP)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest and Topic extraction/clustering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest (machine) learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High concurrency, handling millions of users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of 2011 Bottlenose operated in stealth mode, until we were ready
in December 2011 to launch the Beta version to the public. The launch
was a great success and we got loads of positive &lt;a href=&quot;http://press.bottlenose.com/news&quot;&gt;media coverage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I will continue to work for Bottlenose as their chief architect and allround
(Node.js) developer. I love to see where we will get with Bottlenose in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eu-west-1.beatletech.com/images/bottlenose-beta.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bottlenose.com&quot; height=&quot;128&quot; width=&quot;315&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottlenose = Node.js = #winning&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Malmberg: E-Publishing platform</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2011/07/28/malmberg-e-publishing-platform"/>
   <updated>2011-07-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2011/07/28/malmberg-e-publishing-platform</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The past couple of months have been very busy. First off I was still working partime
for &lt;a href=&quot;http://skylines.net&quot;&gt;Skylines&lt;/a&gt; with which we made it
into &lt;a href=&quot;http://disrupt.techcrunch.com/&quot;&gt;Techcrunch&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dutchdailynews.com/skylines-nyc/&quot;&gt;Disrupt&lt;/a&gt; NY as a
finalist. Skylines was actually the first Dutch startup ever to become a
finalist of this highly rated conference competition. Great stuff,
showing that Amsterdam can be a great place too when it comes to
bootstrapping your global startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, starting in April, I was hired as a Rails developer by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ciber.com/application-development/&quot;&gt;Ciber&lt;/a&gt; on a scrum
project for their client &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.malmberg.nl/Voortgezet-onderwijs/ePack-ICT/Nieuwe-generatie-methodes/Introductie.htm&quot;&gt;Malmberg&lt;/a&gt;,
an educational publisher, to work on the next iteration of their
e-publishing platform. The work consisted of a redesign of the old
platform, and developing a Rails 3 application on top of the existing
data models and MSSQL database (Rails 3 actually works perfectly fine with
other sql dbs besides Mysql and Postgres). The application allows for
teachers to manage their online courses, materials, exams and results,
where students have easy access to all of this. The system is actually
pretty smart in assigning followup courses based on your test scores,
but still gives teachers total control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I can’t show a link to the product or demo, as the
application is currently being tested by the client, and will be rolled
out for the new students in september. However I can say that I like
the end product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe we will see a lot more development in this
area of online learning platforms. Looking for instance at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.khanacademy.org/&quot;&gt;Khan Academy&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://studyflow.com&quot;&gt;Studyflow&lt;/a&gt; we can see that the
landscape is changing. Also a word from my teacher friends tells me that the
Dutch curriculum on both primary and high schools is already filled with more and
more computer courses, that provide custom tailored education for each
individual youngster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed my work at Ciber, working with a great team of skilled
developers, and I don’t rule out that I in the foreseeable future will
be working on next generation learning platforms again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bottlenose closed Beta</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2011/04/26/bottlenose-closed-beta"/>
   <updated>2011-04-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2011/04/26/bottlenose-closed-beta</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I guess most of you have heared about “stealth” startup &lt;a href=&quot;http://bottleno.se&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;, which already got some great pre
release write-ups on &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2011/04/05/bottlenose/&quot;&gt;Techcrunch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://mashable.com/2011/04/05/bottlenose/&quot;&gt;Mashable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you haven’t, Bottlenose describes itself as “a smarter way to surf the Stream. It’s a new
personalization tool that helps the important information find you in
social networks like Twitter and Facebook. Use Bottlenose to track
your interests, visualize trends, and curate knowledge with your
friends.” (Bottleno.se)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands doesn’t feature that many high tech startups, so I was
happy to work together with cofounder &lt;a href=&quot;dominiek.com&quot;&gt;Dominiek
ter Heide&lt;/a&gt; this month (who helped us out last year with our YC company &lt;a href=&quot;newcope.com&quot;&gt;Newcope&lt;/a&gt;).
Armed with Node.js my goal is to, where possible, make the tool even smarter than it already is.
For this challenge it helps a lot to be part of a highly skilled javascript team, who are
pushing the boundaries forward. And besides being a cool high tech product
to work on, I also believe Bottlenose is a must needed solution for an
information overload problem that is getting bigger each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottlenose is currently in alpha, but you can sign up now on &lt;a href=&quot;http://bottleno.se&quot;&gt;Bottleno.se&lt;/a&gt;, and hopefully be one
of the lucky ones for the closed beta to have early access to a tool that will enrich your
twitter and facebook experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eu-west-1.beatletech.com/images/bottlenose.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bottleno.se&quot; height=&quot;157&quot; width=&quot;523&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottlenose = Node.js = #winning&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Skylines 1.0</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2011/03/27/skylines-1-0"/>
   <updated>2011-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2011/03/27/skylines-1-0</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Skylines is a really cool iPhone app that helps you follow what you
like, based on realtime pictures, and for the last couple of weeks I
have been working with the skylines team to create a solid and scalable
backend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week at the SXSW conference we had our 1.0 soft launch and the app is
now available in the app store. We are currently working hard on the
next 1.1 version, which will feature some great additional
options. In the meantime please try out the app, and follow your
interests in a realtime image stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/eu-west-1.beatletech.com/images/skylines.png&quot; alt=&quot;Skylines.net&quot; height=&quot;485&quot; width=&quot;467&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just checkout &lt;a href=&quot;http://skylines.net&quot;&gt;skylines.net&lt;/a&gt; and download
the app from the app store.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>BeatleTech generated with Jekyll</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2011/01/03/beatletech-generated-with-jekyll"/>
   <updated>2011-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2011/01/03/beatletech-generated-with-jekyll</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I started with the creation of BeatleTech.com and blog, I didn’t
want to rely on Wordpress (or others) as I wanted more flexibility and
control, and I definitely didn’t want to separate the blog from the main site,
i.e. linking to a blog on Posterous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my initial plan was to build the site in clojure, given a nice
online clojure blog example, Brian Carper’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/briancarper/cow-blog&quot;&gt;Cow-blog&lt;/a&gt;.
However, shortly after having started, my friend Jeff Rose introduced
me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, which is
a blog-aware, static site generator in Ruby. It allows for templating,
and uses Disqus for showing a dynamic javascript blog. Generating a static
site allowed me to copy all the html files to my Transip webhosting
server, and thereby keeping it extremely low cost. Running a clojure
site on Google App Engine could have been a good alterative, but I
liked giving Jekyll a try. It turned out to be very easy and already has tons of
examples online to check out. I also put the source code of BeatleTech
on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/beatlevic/BeatleTech&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; for sharing, and hope it could be of any use for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you are looking for a way to create your website-blog and
(just like me) already paid for webhosting, which sadly only allows you to do some php
wizardry, then rest assured as Jekyll can save your day.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Cake and Emacs: cake-swank</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2010/12/23/cake-swank"/>
   <updated>2010-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2010/12/23/cake-swank</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So far I have been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/technomancy/leiningen&quot;&gt;leiningen&lt;/a&gt; as my
standard build tool for Clojure, and together with a very nice Emacs
package
called &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.remvee.net/2010/08/19/elein_el_leiningen_functions_for_emacs&quot;&gt;elein&lt;/a&gt;
I was able to run leiningen tasks from within emacs. The functions I use
 most often are elein-swank and elein-reswank to (re)connect with slime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this is all great, but lately an alternative build tool has catched my
eyes and is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ninjudd/cake&quot;&gt;cake&lt;/a&gt;. It features a
persistent JVM, which speeds up startup time tremendeously, and has an
easier way for setting up tasks similar to ruby rake
tasks. Now in order to make my swanking and reswanking work in emacs
with cake I thought of reusing the elein-swank code, but as it turns
out, in order to kill swank I had to kill cake and thereby killing the
persistent JVM (missing the whole purpose). So instead of doing that I
got the advice to just keep swank running, and only reload the
classpath. This resulted in me implementing the following elisp functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-clojure&quot; data-lang=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cake-project-root&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Look for project.clj file to find project root.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;default-directory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;not&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;file-exists-p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;concat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;project.clj&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;concat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;../&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;max&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;expand-file-name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;defmacro&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cake-in-project-root&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Wrap BODY to make 'default-directory' the project root.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;gensym&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;,dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;cake-project-root&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
       &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;,dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
         &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;default-directory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;,dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;,body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
         &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;No cake project root found&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;

&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;cake-swank&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;Connect or reconnect to swank while reloading cake class path files.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;interactive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;slime-connected-p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;slime-disconnect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;buffer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;get-buffer-create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;*cake-swank*&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;flet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;display-buffer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
             &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;buffer-or-name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;optional&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;not-this-window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;frame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;bury-buffer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;buffer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;cake-in-project-root&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;shell-command&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;cake -r&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;buffer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;slime-connect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;127.0.0.1&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;4005&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for this to work one needs to get the latest cake master
version, so you can reload class path files (cake -r). Additionally one has
to turn on swank autostart for cake. This can be done by adding the
line “swank.autostart = localhost:4005” to your .cake/config file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now you can easily switch to cake, keeping reswank in your toolset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tip: If you find yourself always getting the following mini-buffer
message when connecting with slime: “Versions differ: nil (slime)
vs. 20100404 (swank). Continue? (y or n)”, then all you should do is
removing the slime.elc file in your .emacs.d/elpa/slime-X folder, and
consider it history.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>BeatleTech online</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2010/12/19/beatletech-online"/>
   <updated>2010-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2010/12/19/beatletech-online</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With BeatleTech life and kicking, I found it about time to add some blogging
functionality, and to start writing about my ongoing work, research and
serendipity events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my ongoing work you will find me blogging about my emacs journey,
my clojure lessons, rails mambo, and basically any other technology I
will be working with. Further more in my research I will cover topics in
cognitive science, human perception and AI, but all in due time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are in need for an architect, developer or advisor, then know that
BeatleTech is there for you, and Beatle is available for hire!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
