<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>beatltetech.com</title>
 <link href="http://beatletech.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://beatletech.com/"/>
 <updated>2015-02-10T01:37:19+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://beatletech.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Coen Stevens</name>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Bottlenose scores $13.4 Million</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2015/02/09/bottlenose-series-b"/>
   <updated>2015-02-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2015/02/09/bottlenose-series-b</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One and a half years after securing our
&lt;a href=&quot;http://beatletech.com/2013/07/30/bottlenose-secures-four-million/&quot;&gt;$3.6 Million&lt;/a&gt;
series A investment round to bring &#39;Trendfluence&#39; to the enterprise, we are now
proud at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt; to have raised (and
continue to raise) our series B round with a staggering amount of $13.4
Million, bringing the total raised funds north of $17 Million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in December we already disclosed that KPMG International took a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/kpmg-capital-takes-equity-stake-in-bottlenose-a-pioneer-in-real-time-trend-intelligence-300005792.html&quot;&gt;&quot;substantial equity share&quot;&lt;/a&gt; in Bottlenose, but did not yet reveal the
size of the investment nor names of other investors that were ready to
follow KPMG Capital&#39;s lead. Today Techcrunch reported on our Series B
round, listing our additional investors and describing our growing
capabilities in enterprise (real-time) stream data analytics. The
series B round is still open and we plan to raise significant venture
debt on top of the $13.4 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Bottlenose we are having exciting times ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the full story on &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2015/02/09/bottlenose-series-b/&quot;&gt;Techcrunch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My System to Win Big</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2015/02/03/my-system-to-win-big"/>
   <updated>2015-02-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2015/02/03/my-system-to-win-big</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back in January 2014 I read a book by Scott Adams (of Dilbert fame) titled:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17859574-how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big&quot;&gt;&quot;How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big&quot;&lt;/a&gt;.
The book was brought to my attention when I was reading up on some interesting research and ideas on
passion and discipline (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qwOdU02SE0w&quot;&gt;Carl Newport&lt;/a&gt; comes to mind,
explaining why following your passion is bad career advice). Reading Adam&#39;s book definitely struck a
chord with me and even motivated me to change my work flow and long-held believes on what to focus on
in life. Two things stood out for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passion is bullshit. It is only after you have put in the work and are lucky enough in having
success that passion comes, not before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goals are for losers. Systems are for winners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before reading the book I have often asked myself questions like: What is my greatest passion and am I working
every day on the things I&#39;m most passionate about? What kind of startup or company would fit my passion? I
often had a hard time trying to find the perfect answer to these questions, which resulted in
inertia to get started and in some cases I was setting myself up for ever higher and greater goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading about the system approach as an alternative to goal setting made a lot of sense to me. The
system approach can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create habits and reserve your will-power for learning new habits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduce daily decisions to routine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid setting (high) goals, instead have a system that will keep you going&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping up your personal energy, which is your primary metric&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simplicity is key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A system will keep you going, also in moments of failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the key points here is the creation of (good) habits and the discipline to carry it out. A
recent blog post titled:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wisdomination.com/screw-motivation-what-you-need-is-discipline/&quot;&gt;&quot;Screw motivation, what you need is discipline&quot;&lt;/a&gt;
argues for the same point. It basically boils down to growing habits and not let yourself be driven by your emotional state.
So stop waiting until you feel good (enough) to start a particular task and get into the habit of allocating
time to just do stuff to get things done. Focus on the process (your system) and not the product
(deliverables and goals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in general you want to be the most productive you can be, for me having a family with the third kid
on his way (due any moment now), you have to get even more organized and disciplined to get things
done. The way in which I manage this is what I want to present to you
next by outlining my system along several dimensions that Scott describes in his book. I have been adhering to this system for a full year and besides some
minor changes and occasional missteps I&#39;m still following through and it has definitely made a
hugely positive impact on my life and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now without further ado, My System to Win Big:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Exercise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One or more of the following activities I do daily for at least 30 to 60 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sprinting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push-ups / Sit-ups / Plank / Triceps-dips / 7-minute workout cycles (Honestly this is the one I
want to become more of a routine several days a week.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cycling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Sports&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Football (Soccer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kickboxing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Sleep&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say you need a good amount of sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to bed before 00:00 (Yes, this one is hard if you do remote work for US companies from Europe)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sleep 8 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Flexible schedule&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being flexible here means being in charge of your own schedule. Making a fixed planning and schedule for
things you want to do is highly recommended for young parents, as long as you are the one who chooses
to make time for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan holidays/time-off&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan fixed slots for daily exercise and sports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plan stuff that makes you want to get out of bed for it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Diet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m a big proponent of the Paleo lifestyle, and try to avoid as much processed foods as possible and
keeping it real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only occasionally bread/rice/potatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Candy/Cookies/Chips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Sodas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Coffee&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occasionally alcohol (celebrations)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meal skipping is good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fasting once in a while is great (irregular intervals)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Snacks: nuts and fruits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eating more vegetables by improving seasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starches like Oatmeal&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Steadily improving / Skills&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming (Python, Clojure, Julia, Euler, Math)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book reading / knowledge gathering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blogging (on side-projects / programming)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practicing playing the Piano (still a noob here)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.coursera.com&quot;&gt;Coursera courses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Imagine an incredible future&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;related: stay optimistic and opportunistic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Help others&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be there for my kids and wife&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer free advice and guidance for start-ups and companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engage at meetups and help people out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Show gratitude&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Value what you already have&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enjoy the moment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h4&gt;Have a healthy dose of Stoicism&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid the pursuit of materialistic goals and don&#39;t get attached to stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;Final words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My system helped me become more productive and happier overall, which
may not yet be the fame and fortune that Scott Adams achieved, but it is
still a big win to me, and I&#39;m ready when any big opportunity arises
in the future to take it head on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course my system isn&#39;t perfect. Of course my system is tailored to suit me and can be different for you.
Of course I&#39;m still failing every so often, but at least I have my system to hold on to and to
remind me how I want things to go. Get your self into the habit of working on what matters to you
and with a little bit of luck and serendipity you can win big too!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Project brAIn</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2014/09/03/project-brain"/>
   <updated>2014-09-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2014/09/03/project-brain</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After years of talking and thinking about creating our own Artificial Intelligence (AI), &lt;a href=&quot;http://linkedin.com/in/markvoortman&quot;&gt;Mark Voortman&lt;/a&gt; and I finaly decided a couple of months ago to actually start working on it. So project brAIn was born. With brAIn we have the modest goal to build an AI that will change the world as we know it. Using Deep Learning techniques we are building towards some cool applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have launched a new website and wrote an &lt;a href=&quot;http://br-ai-n.com/2014/09/03/introducing-brain/&quot;&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt; with more details on our goals and progress. So check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://br-ai-n.com&quot;&gt;br-ai-n.com&lt;/a&gt; and stay tuned for future posts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://br-ai-n.com/images/screenshot-brAIn-v0.0.2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Skylines.net&quot; height=&quot;485&quot; width=&quot;800&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dokzorg.nl live!</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2013/10/12/dokzorg-live"/>
   <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2013/10/12/dokzorg-live</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I ordered two dedicated machines at Hetzner for myself to develop and run some side projects on a Node.js/MongoDb/Elasticsearch stack.
While these are work in progress, I also finished moving BeatleTech.com to my new server (previously hosted by TransIp) and decided to help out my spouse by
building a website for her freelancing GP (Huisarts) practices. The end result is here today, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://dokzorg.nl&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Dokzorg.nl&lt;/a&gt; is live as of now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She basically wanted a simple landing page with just enough info to get potential employers excited and be findable on the web, without explicitly creating
an online presence by blogging and tweeting. We currently like the end result and hope others like it too. See below for a screenshot of the landing page, and follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://dokzorg.nl&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt; to check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://beatletech.s3.amazonaws.com/dokzorg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dokzorg.nl&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;720&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now after spending some time front-end developing this project,
I&#39;m looking forward to dive back in the other back-end projects I have going for which I can happily ignore HTML and CSS..&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bottlenose secures $3.6 Million</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2013/07/30/bottlenose-secures-four-million"/>
   <updated>2013-07-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2013/07/30/bottlenose-secures-four-million</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bottlenose just secured a $3.6 Million series A round to bring
&#39;Trendfluence&#39; to the Enterprise. With Bottlenose enterprise, while
currently in private beta, we already work with several large brands and
agencies (Pepsi, FleishmanHillard, Razorfish, and DigitasLBi) that
leverage Bottlenose Enterprise for tracking live and emerging trends
and events, directing advertising and marketing initiatives, engaging
customer communities and gathering industry intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the actual press release please check out &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;http://www.novaspivack.com/business/bottlenose-series-a-to-bring-trendfluence-to-the-enterprise&quot;&gt;Nova
Spivack&#39;s blog&lt;/a&gt;
(Bottlenose CEO), or the Techcrunch &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2013/07/30/social-media-dashboard-bottlenose-raises-3-6m/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can keep current momentum at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;, then we have a bright
future ahead of us.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Amsterdam Node meetup group</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2012/04/16/amsterdam-nodejs-meetup"/>
   <updated>2012-04-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2012/04/16/amsterdam-nodejs-meetup</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We (me and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dominiek.com/&quot;&gt;Dominiek ter Heide&lt;/a&gt;) started a new &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/amsnode/&quot;&gt;meetup group&lt;/a&gt; in Amsterdam
for anyone interested in Node.js. We had our first meetup 2 weeks ago,
where Dominiek gave a great introduction to Node, the guys from
Rockstart startup &lt;a href=&quot;http://beta.wercker.com/&quot;&gt;Wercker&lt;/a&gt;
(Continuous deployment made easy) gave a nice overview of all the Node
modules they use, and I gave a talk on when to use
Node and my lessons learned while using Node in my previously Y
combinator funded startup &lt;a href=&quot;http://newcope.com&quot;&gt;Newcope&lt;/a&gt; and in
my current job as Chief architect at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We plan to have the Node meetup bi-monthly on the last Thursday of the
month, so the next meetup will be May 31th at 7:00PM. We
have some interesting speakers lined up so I hope to see you all at our
next or future meetups. You can follow any announcement on &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/amsnode/&quot;&gt;meetup.com&lt;/a&gt; of follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/amsnode&quot;&gt;us&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:800px;text-align:center&quot; id=&quot;__ss_12232685&quot;&gt; &lt;strong style=&quot;display:block;margin:12px 0 4px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/beatlevic/when-to-use-node-lessons-learned&quot; title=&quot;When to use Node? Lessons learned&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;When to use Node? Lessons learned&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/12232685&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;355&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;padding:5px 0 12px&quot;&gt; View more &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;presentations&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/beatlevic&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;beatlevic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Node.js = #winning&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for those of you who love Clojure or like to know more about it,
check out the &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/The-Amsterdam-Clojure-Meetup-Group/&quot;&gt;
Amsterdam Clojure meetup.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bottlenose 2012</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2012/01/04/bottlenose-2012"/>
   <updated>2012-01-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2012/01/04/bottlenose-2012</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The past couple of months I have been busy working for &lt;a
href=&quot;http://bottlenose.com&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;, for which I did some work
before (earlier in 2011). As I wrote about Bottlenose in a previous
post, it is a really cool (American) tech startup partly based in the
Netherlands that is building a new social assistance application that
helps you make sense of all your social activity streams. It helps
navigate the depths of your networks and keep up with your social
streams so you can engage more intelligently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoy working on all the technical challenges that we need to
tackle to create a smart and intelligent client. Challenges involving:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Natural Language Processing (NLP)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest and Topic extraction/clustering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest (machine) learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High concurrency, handling millions of users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Most of 2011 Bottlenose operated in stealth mode, until we were ready
in December 2011 to launch the Beta version to the public. The launch
was a great success and we got loads of positive &lt;a href=&quot;http://press.bottlenose.com/news&quot;&gt;media coverage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I will continue to work for Bottlenose as their chief architect and allround
(Node.js) developer. I love to see where we will get with Bottlenose in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/beatletech/bottlenose-beta.png&quot;
alt=&quot;Bottlenose.com&quot; height=&quot;128&quot; width=&quot;315&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottlenose = Node.js = #winning&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Malmberg: E-Publishing platform</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2011/07/28/malmberg-e-publishing-platform"/>
   <updated>2011-07-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2011/07/28/malmberg-e-publishing-platform</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The past couple of months have been very busy. First off I was still working partime
for &lt;a href=&quot;http://skylines.net&quot;&gt;Skylines&lt;/a&gt; with which we made it
into &lt;a href=&quot;http://disrupt.techcrunch.com/&quot;&gt;Techcrunch&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.dutchdailynews.com/skylines-nyc/&quot;&gt;Disrupt&lt;/a&gt; NY as a
finalist. Skylines was actually the first Dutch startup ever to become a
finalist of this highly rated conference competition. Great stuff,
showing that Amsterdam can be a great place too when it comes to
bootstrapping your global startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, starting in April, I was hired as a Rails developer by &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.ciber.com/application-development/&quot;&gt;Ciber&lt;/a&gt; on a scrum
project for their client &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.malmberg.nl/Voortgezet-onderwijs/ePack-ICT/Nieuwe-generatie-methodes/Introductie.htm&quot;&gt;Malmberg&lt;/a&gt;,
an educational publisher, to work on the next iteration of their
e-publishing platform. The work consisted of a redesign of the old
platform, and developing a Rails 3 application on top of the existing
data models and MSSQL database (Rails 3 actually works perfectly fine with
other sql dbs besides Mysql and Postgres). The application allows for
teachers to manage their online courses, materials, exams and results,
where students have easy access to all of this. The system is actually
pretty smart in assigning followup courses based on your test scores,
but still gives teachers total control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I can&#39;t show a link to the product or demo, as the
application is currently being tested by the client, and will be rolled
out for the new students in september. However I can say that I like
the end product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe we will see a lot more development in this
area of online learning platforms. Looking for instance at the &lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.khanacademy.org/&quot;&gt;Khan Academy&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a
href=&quot;http://studyflow.com&quot;&gt;Studyflow&lt;/a&gt; we can see that the
landscape is changing. Also a word from my teacher friends tells me that the
Dutch curriculum on both primary and high schools is already filled with more and
more computer courses, that provide custom tailored education for each
individual youngster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed my work at Ciber, working with a great team of skilled
developers, and I don&#39;t rule out that I in the foreseeable future will
be working on next generation learning platforms again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bottlenose closed Beta</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2011/04/26/bottlenose-closed-beta"/>
   <updated>2011-04-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2011/04/26/bottlenose-closed-beta</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I guess most of you have heared about &quot;stealth&quot; startup &lt;a
href=&quot;http://bottleno.se&quot;&gt;Bottlenose&lt;/a&gt;, which already got some great pre
release write-ups on &lt;a
href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2011/04/05/bottlenose/&quot;&gt;Techcrunch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
href=&quot;http://mashable.com/2011/04/05/bottlenose/&quot;&gt;Mashable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you haven&#39;t, Bottlenose describes itself as &quot;a smarter way to surf the Stream. It&#39;s a new
personalization tool that helps the important information find you in
social networks like Twitter and Facebook. Use Bottlenose to track
your interests, visualize trends, and curate knowledge with your
friends.&quot; (Bottleno.se)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Netherlands doesn&#39;t feature that many high tech startups, so I was
happy to work together with cofounder &lt;a href=&quot;dominiek.com&quot;&gt;Dominiek
ter Heide&lt;/a&gt; this month (who helped us out last year with our YC company &lt;a href=&quot;newcope.com&quot;&gt;Newcope&lt;/a&gt;).
Armed with Node.js my goal is to, where possible, make the tool even smarter than it already is.
For this challenge it helps a lot to be part of a highly skilled javascript team, who are
pushing the boundaries forward. And besides being a cool high tech product
to work on, I also believe Bottlenose is a must needed solution for an
information overload problem that is getting bigger each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottlenose is currently in alpha, but you can sign up now on &lt;a
href=&quot;http://bottleno.se&quot;&gt;Bottleno.se&lt;/a&gt;, and hopefully be one
of the lucky ones for the closed beta to have early access to a tool that will enrich your
twitter and facebook experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://beatletech.s3.amazonaws.com/bottlenose.png&quot;
alt=&quot;Bottleno.se&quot; height=&quot;157&quot; width=&quot;523&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bottlenose = Node.js = #winning&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Skylines 1.0</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2011/03/27/skylines-1-0"/>
   <updated>2011-03-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2011/03/27/skylines-1-0</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Skylines is a really cool iPhone app that helps you follow what you
like, based on realtime pictures, and for the last couple of weeks I
have been working with the skylines team to create a solid and scalable
backend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week at the SXSW conference we had our 1.0 soft launch and the app is
now available in the app store. We are currently working hard on the
next 1.1 version, which will feature some great additional
options. In the meantime please try out the app, and follow your
interests in a realtime image stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://beatletech.s3.amazonaws.com/skylines.png&quot; alt=&quot;Skylines.net&quot; height=&quot;485&quot; width=&quot;467&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just checkout &lt;a href=&quot;http://skylines.net&quot;&gt;skylines.net&lt;/a&gt; and download
the app from the app store.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>BeatleTech generated with Jekyll</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2011/01/03/beatletech-generated-with-jekyll"/>
   <updated>2011-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2011/01/03/beatletech-generated-with-jekyll</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I started with the creation of BeatleTech.com and blog, I didn&#39;t
want to rely on Wordpress (or others) as I wanted more flexibility and
control, and I definitely didn&#39;t want to separate the blog from the main site,
i.e. linking to a blog on Posterous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my initial plan was to build the site in clojure, given a nice
online clojure blog example, Brian Carper&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/briancarper/cow-blog&quot;&gt;Cow-blog&lt;/a&gt;.
However, shortly after having started, my friend Jeff Rose introduced
me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, which is
a blog-aware, static site generator in Ruby. It allows for templating,
and uses Disqus for showing a dynamic javascript blog. Generating a static
site allowed me to copy all the html files to my Transip webhosting
server, and thereby keeping it extremely low cost. Running a clojure
site on Google App Engine could have been a good alterative, but I
liked giving Jekyll a try. It turned out to be very easy and already has tons of
examples online to check out. I also put the source code of BeatleTech
on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/beatlevic/BeatleTech&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; for sharing, and hope it could be of any use for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you are looking for a way to create your website-blog and
(just like me) already paid for webhosting, which sadly only allows you to do some php
wizardry, then rest assured as Jekyll can save your day.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Cake and Emacs: cake-swank</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2010/12/23/cake-swank"/>
   <updated>2010-12-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2010/12/23/cake-swank</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So far I have been using &lt;a
href=&quot;https://github.com/technomancy/leiningen&quot;&gt;leiningen&lt;/a&gt; as my
standard build tool for Clojure, and together with a very nice Emacs
package
called &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.remvee.net/2010/08/19/elein_el_leiningen_functions_for_emacs&quot;&gt;elein&lt;/a&gt;
I was able to run leiningen tasks from within emacs. The functions I use
 most often are elein-swank and elein-reswank to (re)connect with slime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this is all great, but lately an alternative build tool has catched my
eyes and is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ninjudd/cake&quot;&gt;cake&lt;/a&gt;. It features a
persistent JVM, which speeds up startup time tremendeously, and has an
easier way for setting up tasks similar to ruby rake
tasks. Now in order to make my swanking and reswanking work in emacs
with cake I thought of reusing the elein-swank code, but as it turns
out, in order to kill swank I had to kill cake and thereby killing the
persistent JVM (missing the whole purpose). So instead of doing that I
got the advice to just keep swank running, and only reload the
classpath. This resulted in me implementing the following elisp functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;cake-project-root&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Look for project.clj file to find project root.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;default-directory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;max &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;not &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;&amp;gt; max &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;file-exists-p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;concat &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;project.clj&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;concat &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;cwd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;../&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;max &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;- max &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;expand-file-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;found&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;defmacro &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;cake-in-project-root&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Wrap BODY to make `default-directory&amp;#39; the project root.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;gensym&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;cake-project-root&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt;
         &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;default-directory&lt;/span&gt; ,&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; ,&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;body&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
         &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;error&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;No cake project root found&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;cake-swank&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Connect or reconnect to swank while reloading cake class path files.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;interactive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;slime-connected-p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;slime-disconnect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;let &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;buffer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;get-buffer-create&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;*cake-swank*&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;flet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;display-buffer&lt;/span&gt;
             &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;buffer-or-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;optional&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;not-this-window&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;frame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;bury-buffer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;buffer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;cake-in-project-root&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;shell-command&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;cake -r&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;buffer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;slime-connect&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;127.0.0.1&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;4005&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In order for this to work one needs to get the latest cake master
version, so you can reload class path files (cake -r). Additionally one has
to turn on swank autostart for cake. This can be done by adding the
line &quot;swank.autostart = localhost:4005&quot; to your .cake/config file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now you can easily switch to cake, keeping reswank in your toolset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tip: If you find yourself always getting the following mini-buffer
message when connecting with slime: &quot;Versions differ: nil (slime)
vs. 20100404 (swank). Continue? (y or n)&quot;, then all you should do is
removing the slime.elc file in your .emacs.d/elpa/slime-X folder, and
consider it history.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>BeatleTech online</title>
   <link href="http://beatletech.com/2010/12/19/beatletech-online"/>
   <updated>2010-12-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://beatletech.com/2010/12/19/beatletech-online</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With BeatleTech life and kicking, I found it about time to add some blogging
functionality, and to start writing about my ongoing work, research and
serendipity events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my ongoing work you will find me blogging about my emacs journey,
my clojure lessons, rails mambo, and basically any other technology I
will be working with. Further more in my research I will cover topics in
cognitive science, human perception and AI, but all in due time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are in need for an architect, developer or advisor, then know that
BeatleTech is there for you, and Beatle is available for hire!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>
